Joseph Modica (1946-2018) Collection
Visual AIDS Archive
Joseph Modica (1946-2018) Collection
Visual AIDS Archive
30 Linear Feet
5 document boxes, 15 slide boxes, 5 large boxes, 2 smaller boxes,
Biographical / Historical
Joseph Modica (1946-2018) was born in 1946 in Staten Island and attended High School of Music and Art, Staten Island Community College and the School of Visual Arts. In the 1960s, Modica was part of a nascent gay and lesbian community on Staten Island and close with the artist Ned Asta and writer Larry Mitchell (author of The Faggots and Their Friends Between Revolutions, illustrated by Asta).
Modica was an avid photographer beginning in the late 1960s, documenting his circle of friends in Staten Island and, after moving to the East Village in the 1970s, the downtown New York club scene. His photographs from the 1980s chronicle spaces such as the Pyramid Club and Danceteria, featuring luminaries Divine, Ethyl Eichelberger, Keith Haring, and John Sex. During this time Modica also worked as a graphic designer and photographed male nudes for the pornographic serial Straight to Hell. Modica's photographs also document New York gay activism and several years of pride parades. After the year 2000, as he suffered from the effects of illness and depression, he turned away from photography and dedicated himself to life drawing, producing hundreds of male figure drawings over the next decade.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials associated with both Joseph Modica's artistic practice and his personal life. Materials include photographic prints, 35mm slides, photographic negatives, papers, ephemera, periodicals, publications, press clippings, personal correspondence, and sketches. This collection consists of materials spanning from 1970-2017.
Notable subjects in this collection include Straight to Hell, Danceteria, New York nightlife, pride parades, the NYU wrestling team, Studio 54, The Pyramid Club, Limelight, Show Palace, Bad Boys, and Trax. Notable figures who appear in Modica's photographs include Ethyl Eichelberger, Divine, Keith Haring, John Sex, Boyd McDonald, Quentin Crisp, Divine, Boy George, and Sylvester.
Custodial History
Joseph Modica's collection was cared for upon his death by Dominic Ambrose and Rosine Signoriello and was donated to Visual AIDS in March 2025.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection were kept mostly in original order and all original folders are included. The folders were arranged in alphabetical order.
Series are organized according to Joseph Modica's original filing system. The Slide Photographs series were originally organized together in binders separate from the materials that make up the Photographs and Design Work Files series. The Drawings and Oversized Materials series consists of materials originally housed in large art portfolios. File names come from Joseph Modica's original file naming system.
General
For questions about this collection or to request permissions for reproductions, email archive@visualaids.org
- Photographs and Design Work Files
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains artwork made by Joseph Modica as well as materials produced surrounding his artistic practice. These materials include photographic prints, 35mm slides, 35mm negatives, contact sheets, papers, correspondence, book covers, proofs of work, and ephemera. Though widely undated, these materials span the 1970s-2000s.
  Arrangement
  Materials in this series have been kept in original order as much as possible. Folders names are taken directly from Joseph Modica's original filing system.
  - Box 1, Folder 1: ACT UP Benefit - Leslie Gore at MK (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 2: AIDS Dance Benefit PS 122 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 3: Alan Reust Portraits (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 4: Bad Boys #2 - Basic Bad Boys - Limelight - Keioki Dancing (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 5: Bad Boys #4 - Safe Sex (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 6: Bad Boys #9 - STH Best Butt Danceteria - Hapi Phace + Pyramid Drag Queens - John Reed (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 7: Bad Boys 8 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 8: Bad Boys Anniversary - Danceteria - Circle Jerk - Diane Brill - Michael Musto - Bad Boys At Siberia '88 - Jimmy James as Judy (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 9: Bad Boys II (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 10: Bad Boys Straight to Hell Final Show (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 11: Bad Boys Wrestling - Limelight (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 12: Bartenders for NY Native + ATR Poster (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 13: Beach Candids (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 14: Beaches/Pool/Pier negatives (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 15: "Body Beautiful" Duplex Party - Limelight (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 16: Boxing - Danceteria (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 17: Boy Bar: Drag, The Larmons, Danceteria (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 18: Boyd McDonald + Quentin Crisp Portraits (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 19: Brideshead (TV) (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 20: Bridget (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 21: Club stuff/events negatives (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 22: Construction (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 23: Danceteria - 10,000 Maniacs (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 24: Dell Book Covers (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 25: Diane Brill's Millionaire's Fashions -Palladium (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 26: Divine - Pizza-A-Go-Go + Look Alike Contest - 1981 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 27: Divine and Stripping Photos (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 28: Dream Boys" - Limelight (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 29: Ethyl Eichelberger - SNAFU (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 30: Family and Friends (1 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 31: Family and Friends (2 of 4) (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 32: Family and Friends (3 of 4) - Dom in BA - Dick + Jill, Tina/Lance Family Lobster Ride (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 33: Family and Friends (4 of 4) - New Years Eve '90 - LH, Ruby, Ned, Yvonne, Sal, Taz (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 34: Family negatives (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 35: Fashion - Menza and Brazilian Fashion - Limelight (Box 1)
  - Box 2, Folder 1: Florida (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 2: Florida Strippers, Tony Z Limelight, July 4 Party (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 3: Friends (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 4: Friends Negatives (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 5: Gaultier, "Le Defile" + Betsey Johnson (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 6: Gay Pride negatives (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 7: Gay Pride Proclamation (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 8: Gayiety Strip - International Crisis Show - Mark D'Aleo - Backstage + Time Expo (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 9: Helicopters Over NYC (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 10: Holly Woodlawn - James Siena, Chase, John Sex (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 11: "Inevitable Love: Safe Sex" - Limelight (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 12: IZOT - Cruising the Movies - At the Follies Stripping (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 13: Jamie James as Marilyn + Judy - Trax (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 14: Jean Hill Party - Area (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 15: Jefferson Airplane - Central Park (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 16: Katherine Hamnett Fashion, Tomas and Sal, Charles Jordan, Martina (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 17: Kenneth Cole, Annie Liebowitz + Models, Zette @ Area, Apollo Talent Show, Robin Williams (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 18: Leo Ford + Dancers - Area + Limelight (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 19: Leo Ford with Killer Pussy - Area (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 20: LH Summer 85/Thanksgiving 82 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 21: Lifeguard Competition (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 22: Lounge Lizards (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 23: MacDougal Roof + Window Shots (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 24: Men Without Clothes - Area (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 25: Miscellaneous "To Be Printed" (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 26: Miscellaneous Negatives (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 27: Miscellaneous Photos (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 28: Miscellaneous Prints (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 29: Miscellaneous Prints and Art Book (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 30: Miscellaneous Prints and Negatives (1 of 3) (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 31: Miscellaneous Prints and Negatives (2 of 3) (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 32: Miscellaneous Prints and Negatives (3 of 3) (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 33: Miscellaneous Scanned Prints (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 34: NY Beaches, Staten Island Beach and Pool (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 35: NYU Locker Room 1985 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 36: NYU Locker Room 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 37: NYU Wrestling - Bulgaria vs US - 1989 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 38: NYU Wrestling 1986 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 39: NYU Wrestling Negatives (Box 2)
  - Box 3, Folder 1: NYU Wrestling Prints (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 2: "On Tina Tuna Walk" Materials (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 3: P-Town (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 4: Pagan Place - Palladium (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 5: Party for "The Ritz" Play (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 6: Performance/events negatives (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 7: Personal Photographs (1960s-70s) (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 8: Personal Photographs (Horse + Dog, Rex) (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 9: Phoenix Strippers, Mr Leather (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 10: Photo Book Materials (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 11: Pitt St Pool + Tompkins Square Park Basketball - 1986 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 12: Pop Tarts, Zette, John Sex, TV (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 13: Pride '86 - Christopher St Days - 1982 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 14: Pride '86 - Dean Johnson (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 15: Pride '89 + '91 Negatives (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 16: Pride Photo Slides (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 17: Pyramid - Eduardo Cartagena, Ethyl Eichelberger, STH (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 18: Pyramid - Eric Ryan - Victor Weaver, STH (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 19: Pyramid and Danceteria - Roger aka Frank Vickers (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 20: Red Hot Chili Peppers (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 21: Rolling Stones Photos (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 22: Salambo + White Whore (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 23: Scots/Charleton Heston - Central Park (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 24: Self-portraits (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 25: "Silver People" + Mr. NYC - Limelight (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 26: "Sketcher X" Proof (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 27: Slides labeled "To Lighten" (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 28: Stanton St - Rick M: Faces - Ned (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 29: STH at The Tunnel (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 30: STH Best Butt #1 at The Tunnel (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 31: STH Cover Boy - Danceteria + STH Cute Boy - Pop Tarts (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 32: STH Coverboy - Danceteria - 1985 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 33: STH Go-Go (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 34: STH Stripping for Money + Best Butt #3 (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 35: STH Wet Jockeys (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 36: Streets (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 37: Streets (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 38: Streets/Construction/Ferry Negatives (Box 3)
  - Box 3, Folder 39: Strippers at Majique/Underground - Mr. Jock - Danny Bozar (Box 3)
  - Box 4, Folder 1: Studio 54 - Gym Night - Wil Higgins Party - Boy George (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 2: Studio 54 Lifesavers (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 3: Studio 54 Lingerie Fashion Show (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 4: Sylvester (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 5: Tango Night - Limelight (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 6: Thomson Family/Bob and Missy (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 7: Tony Nunz and Tom Spanbauer (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 8: Trax AIDS Benefit, Show Palace, Wig Ball (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 9: Truro '90 (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 10: TV (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 11: TV Negatives (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 12: Unconscious Lovers (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 13: Union Wrestling + Area Wrestling (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 14: Vacations negatives (Box 4)
  - Box 4, Folder 15: "Very mixed" slides (Box 4)
- Personal Papers
  This series includes personal materials including correspondence, journals, exhibition materials, sketches, pornographic materials, and ephemera.
  - Box 5, Folder 1: Awards and Certificates (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 2: Celebrity Photos and Autographs (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 3: Correspondence (In Touch and First Hand) (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 4: Donation Information (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 5: Doodles (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 6: Exhibition Announcements (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 7: Handwritten Notes and Emails (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 8: Magazine Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 9: Miscellaneous Papers (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 10: Personal Identification Materials (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 11: Personal Notebooks (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 12: Personal Papers (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 13: Personal Photos and Notes (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 14: Personal Writings (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 15: Personal Writings and Dreams (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 16: Political Buttons (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 17: Pornographic Materials (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 18: Pornographic Materials (1 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 19: Pornographic Materials (2 of 2) (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 20: Pornographic Publications (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 21: Postcards (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 22: Publications and Maps (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 23: Resumes, Cover Letters, Invoices (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 24: Sketches (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 25: Visual AIDS (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 26: Visual AIDS - Grants and Postcards (Box 5)
  - Box 5, Folder 27: Writing, Lists, Personal Papers (Box 5)
- Slide Photography
  This series of slide boxes contains 35mm slides, negatives, contact sheets, and some photographic prints of both personal and professional photography. This series includes materials from 1970-1988.
  Materials in this series consist of slides housed separate from the photographic work in the Photographs and Design Work Files series in binders. The labels come from the original slide sheets as well as from labels on the outside of original binders.
  - Box 6 – Glenn Swann, Mr. Leather, Bob Sandor, James - New Orleans, Scorpio - MacDougal & Sal's, Eduardo, Cerebrum - Staten Island Community College, Indi (Box 6)
  - Box 7 – Tom Young, Eduardo, Fritz, Nikki, Billy, Gary Casanova, Danny, Davey Hernandez, Scorpio (Box 7)
  - Box 8 – Models: Mark D'Aleo, Jason, Wayne, Len, Mike Carr, Miscellaneous; Body builders, Beacon, Danceteria mud wrestling, Scots - Central Park, Firemen 84, Studio 54 Gym Night, Lingerie, Better Bods, Madison Ave Muscle, Union Club, Tony Z Limelite (Box 8)
  - Box 9 – LH SI, Miscellaneous Slides (Box 9)
  - Box 10 – Bad Boy 88, Mark D'Aleo, Bob Sandor, Hammock - clothed, Bedroom, James - New Orleans, Published - Giacino (Honcho), Mario Listo (Honcho), Scorpio (Firsthand) (Box 10)
  - Box 11 – Personal photographs (Box 11)
  - Box 12 – Bob Sandor (Box 12)
  - Box 13 – Indio, Frank Kennedy, Tom Doldon, Jaimie Bleu, Antonio Moreno, Mario Castro, Malibu '70, Dream Canyon, Peaceful Valley, Boulder 70, Yosemite/Yellowstone/Gunsight/Palo Alto, Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Box 14 – Bad Boys Anniversary, Backstage circle jerk, Wrestling Limelite, Bad Boys 9, Bad Boys Danceteria, Bad Boys Jason, Best Bad Boys '88 @ Siberia, Frank Kennedy, Unlabeled (Box 14)
  - Box 15 – Til Tuesday - Simon F, Grease, John Sex, Theatre Street, Studio 52, Joe Jackson/10,000 Maniacs, 60s Concerts, White Whore, East Village fashions, Defile Palladium, TV/Movies, Bob Hope, Helen Hayes, Lucy, Puerto Rico '86 (Box 15)
  - Box 16 – Speedy (Eric), Cesar Monroy, Alain Ruest, Glenn Swann, Kevin Wallace, Steve Potter, Michael, Untitled, Stonewall 25, Cheryl's Going party, Poor Rex, JT Assaulted, Summer Canada, AntiWar World, TugBook Two, SI Woodstock (Box 16)
  - Box 17 – Show Palace AIDS Benefit Trax, Gay Pride 1986, Gay Pride 1982 - Christopher St Parade, Trax Gay Pride Day - AIDS Benefit, Spirit + Flesh - Saint Carla Dunlap, 21 Club dancers - Fort Lauderdale, Dancers at The Building, John Sex - Limelight, ACT UP Halloween Party, Gayiety Show, Best Butt II, Tunnel, Straight to Hell Parties, Best Lifeguards, Miscellaneous, Salombo Backstage, Salombo Onstage, 60's, NY Snow, '05 Rag Project, Art Portfolio Slides (Box 17)
  - Box 18 – Red Party P-town Eldridge, Acapulco, Mexico w/ Paul and Claudia, SF Baker Beach - Rich + Terry, Rob + Tina, SABA Last Day, St Martin (Box 18)
  - Box 19 – Joseph Kathy show/Steven Diverte, memory cards, Vatican/Mitch's table, Juda + Lee cabin, LH Party, cut up flash negs, LH winter 75-76, Bald Mitch + Rick, Mitch/Sal Summer NY - 3rd St, Shorts at Sheridan Square/Christopher St, Key West, Andy and Tony, Bald Jose, Halloween 76, unlabeled (Box 19)
  - Box 20 – Unlabeled, Intern, Cornell Dance, Pink Satin, Land meeting, Cabin/LH, Clearwater, Winter LH - wiki/David/Ned/Jose/Luna, Neddy, Luna, Jose, David/Snow/Wiki/Peter Provok, Reservoir (Year of Watkins Concert), Yvonne in LH Kitchen, Luna, Luna/Neddy/Jose in the snow, Boston - David Moore/Rich Goldman/State St. Apt, J Troy Windows, Unlabeled/loose negatives, Early LH, Calvin, Key West, Watkins Glen - concert trash, Hedda, Shana, Building A-frame, Jada Spring St with Cat, Mitch and Phoebe, Sunny on the road, from kick's show, P-town, Richard, intensify, paintings (card), various personal photos (Box 20)
- Drawings and Oversized Materials
  This series of materials includes primarily original artwork in the form of large sketches as well as graphic design proofs, some photographs, publications, and periodicals.
  - Box 21 – sketches (Box 21)
  - Box 22 – design work, publications, periodicals (Box 22)
  - Box 23 – sketches (Box 23)
  - Box 24 – sketches (Box 24)
  - Box 25 – sketches, design work (Box 25)
  - Box 26 – sketches, publications, personal notebooks, photography, and ephemera (Box 26)
  - Box 27 – sketches and photography (Box 27)